A Guide to the Charles Burton Fahs papers FA099
Rockefeller Archive Center
Charles Burton Fahs papers
1838, 1908-1993, Bulk 1908-1980
bulk
Rockefeller Archive Center
Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton), 1908-1980
FA099
5 Cubic Feet Extent is approximate
12 document boxes and 5 oversize boxes.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted are noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Related Archival Materials note
Rockefeller Foundation records, particularly Record Group 12, Officers’ Diaries.
John D. Rockefeller 3rd Papers, Asian Interests subseries (Series 1.3 and 3.5).
Copies of select Charles Burton Fahs publications and files within the Charles Burton Fahs Papers are also available at the Northwestern University Archives.
Scope and Contents note
The Charles Burton Fahs Papers contain materials on the life and career of Charles Burton Fahs, as well as personal materials about his family, including parents Sophia Lyon Fahs and Charles Harvey Fahs, wife Jamie Ross Fahs, and children James Harvey Fahs and Barbara Ruth Fahs Charles.
Prior to sending her husband’s papers to the Rockefeller Archive Center, Jamie annotated many of the documents and letters included in the collection. These notes generally indicate the relationship between Burton and the other individual or a piece of family history that is not extant in the document but which she felt was relevant. Her notations can be fact, anecdote, or opinion. Her notes were retained in the collection and can be found with the relevant document.
Arrangement note
Jamie Ross Fahs’s prior handling and use of her husband’s papers, as well as the complexity of the files, necessitated the creation of a new arrangement for these papers. The Charles Burton Fahs Papers are arranged in six series, as follows:
Series 1 Personal Papers; Series 2 Professional Papers; Series 3 Professional Correspondence; Series 4 Manuscripts, Publications, and Speeches; Series 5 Awards and Citations; Series 6 Photographs
Biographical/Historical note
Charles Burton Fahs was born in Brooklyn, New York on September 8, 1908. His parents, Sophia (Sophie) Lyon Fahs and Charles Harvey Fahs, who went by Harvey, raised Burton and his sisters Dorothy, Ruth (who died in childhood), and Lois in Brooklyn, New Jersey, and California. Harvey traveled a great deal for his job and was often absent from the family home, leaving Sophie to raise the children on her own. The Fahs parents encouraged exploration and independent thinking among their children and were a very close-knit family, despite Harvey’s lengthy absences.
Following the Fahs family tradition, Burton attended Northwestern University in Evanston, Illinois for his undergraduate study, majoring in political science. He also displayed a keen interest for international studies and comparative politics, and he pursued these interests in class as well as in his extracurricular activities, primarily through his membership in the Institute for Oriental Students. Here he met many international students, engaged in discussions and debates over current events, and began to explore diverse cultures through the life experiences of other students.
Burton completed his undergraduate studies in 1929 and traveled to Europe for the summer. During the 1929-1930 school year, he attended the University of Berlin and enriched his language skills. Burton also attended a variety of German student political meetings, furthering his interest in current events and political systems.
For the 1930-1931 school year, Burton returned to Northwestern to begin his graduate studies. Burton met Jamie Ross sometime during this period, and they became engaged in 1931 after Burton completed his master’s thesis and exams. Jamie had been raised in Colorado Springs, Colorado and had come to Northwestern for a master’s degree in Classics. She remained in Evanston after the completion of her degree and worked as a Latin instructor during the couple’s courtship and early marriage. Burton and Jamie were married in Colorado Springs, Colorado on June 27, 1932.
Burton continued his studies during the early years of their marriage, receiving his PhD in 1933 and embarking on three years of study in Japanese language, culture, and politics, first in Paris and then in Kyoto and Tokyo. Jamie traveled with her husband during these years, and the two lived frugally but comfortably on Burton’s fellowship stipend. During the year in Paris, Burton and Jamie met Edwin O. Reischauer, a lifelong friend and the American Ambassador to Japan during Burton’s employment at the U.S. Embassy in Tokyo. In 1935, their son James Harvey Fahs was born in Kyoto.
In 1937, the Fahs family returned to the United States and Burton began his academic career as an instructor, and later an assistant professor, at Pomona College in Claremont, California. The family planned for an eighteen month sabbatical in Japan and China for 1940-1941, but their plans abruptly changed with the imminent threat of war. After arriving in Japan, it was decided that Jamie and Jimmie should return to the U.S. while Burton would continue on to China, where he stayed for several months before rejoining his family in California.
Burton took a leave of absence from Pomona and joined the Office of Strategic Services in the fall of 1941. The family relocated to the Washington, D.C. area, where daughter Barbara Ruth was born in 1943. Burton remained with OSS for the duration of the war, eventually being promoted to Chief of the Research and Analysis Division (Far East). Between October 1944 and February 1945, Burton traveled to China, Burma, and India to assess various overseas research units.
At the conclusion of World War II, Burton resigned from Pomona College. Within a year, he also resigned from the Department of State (where the Research and Analysis Division had been transferred at the conclusion of the war) to accept a position with the Rockefeller Foundation as Assistant Director in the Humanities Division. In 1950, Burton was appointed Director of the Humanities Division. The Fahs family lived in Fair Lawn, New Jersey during this period. Jamie was elected to the local school board and became involved in Girl Scouts. Burton traveled a great deal for his job with the Rockefeller Foundation, often visiting other parts of the U.S. or foreign countries for 4-6 week periods.
In 1961, Burton resigned from the Rockefeller Foundation. By 1962, he was appointed Minister-Counselor for Cultural and Public Affairs in the Embassy of the United States in Tokyo, Japan. This appointment was unique and created specifically to match Burton’s educational background and talents. The intervention of friends like Dean Rusk and Edwin Reischauer smoothed the way for the creation of this position. Burton and Jamie returned to Tokyo, and both were extremely busy with diplomatic duties and the attendant expectations and social obligations which accompany such a position. During this time, both of their children married; Barbara had her ceremony in Tokyo.
Burton remained with the Embassy in Tokyo until 1967, and once again the Fahses returned to the United States. Burton accepted a one year academic position as Harry C. Trexler Distinguished Visiting Professor at Muhlenberg College in Allentown, Pennsylvania. The following year, Burton was appointed Director of International Studies at Miami University in Miami, Ohio. He and Jamie moved to Oxford, Ohio and settled into a new home. Jamie returned to academic life as well, tutoring students in Latin.
Burton and Jamie retired from Miami University in 1973, traveling internationally in their retirement and spending time with their growing family. Burton continued his work with Grolier, Inc. during this time, beginning a project to publish a set of encyclopedias in Japanese. This project would ultimately be abandoned.
Beginning in 1975, Burton experienced serious health problems related to terminal illness. He kept his illness at bay for several years, but his health began to fail significantly in late 1979. It was also this year that marks the presentation of two significant awards, an honorary degree from Miami University and the Japan Foundation Award. Despite his declining health, special arrangements were made so that Burton could travel to Japan to accept this award. Jamie, Jim, and Barbara accompanied him for this momentous occasion.
Charles Burton Fahs died on February 26, 1980 at the age of 71. A memorial service was held at the Sesquicentennial Chapel at Miami University on March 1, and Burton’ ashes were interred in the Oxford Cemetery on August 24 of the same year.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Charles Burton Fahs Papers were donated to the Rockefeller Archive Center by Mrs. Jamie Ross Fahs, Fahs’s widow, in several accretions between the years 1984 and 1994, including Accession 1985:061.
Philippines; Japan; Photographs; Travel
- Personal papers, 1838, 1908-1993; 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of family materials and correspondence, as well as several versions of a biography of Charles Burton Fahs compiled and written by Jamie Ross Fahs. This series also contains information on Burton’s education, and his illness and death. There are files of correspondence and clippings which post-date Burton’s death; these materials were received and collected by Jamie Ross Fahs and were included in the collection because of their connection to Burton’s life and career.
  The correspondence folders are extremely rich and detailed and provide a window into the lives and activities of Burton and Jamie throughout their lives. Folders which begin with the word Correspondence indicate that the letters in the file are written by Burton. Incoming correspondence is rare, and there are no letters between the spouses.
  Correspondence from Burton’s childhood includes letters written or received by his parents, as well as maternal aunt Abbie Lyon Sharman, her husband Harry Sharman, and maternal uncle D. Willard Lyon and his wife Grace. Burton was a regular correspondent with his family during his college and graduate school years. After they were married, Burton and Jamie took turns writing to his family. There are also a few letters to Jamie’s mother. Both Burton and Jamie were faithful correspondents, writing every one to two weeks. The letters dating from 1933-1936, when they lived abroad, are particularly fascinating for the details they offer of living conditions and adjustments to cultural differences. During Burton’s career at the Embassy, Jamie served as the family’s main correspondent and wrote lengthy letters about both of their activities and travels in Asia. Annual Christmas letters for the years 1951 through 1980 detail the family life of the Fahses and is the primary source of information about their lives during the period 1951-1961.
  The files relating to the biography (or biographies) of Charles Burton Fahs all draw from the same material and build upon each other. Jamie’s first biography was based on the oral history interview of Burton conducted by Caroline Bailey at the time of the donation of Burton’s library to Earlham College. To this she added an extensive chronology of his life and selected correspondence and writings. Finally Jamie and her daughter Barbara attempted a full biography, a draft of which is included. Jamie also corresponded with Burton’s colleagues and their friends for comments on the biography draft and for additional information to enhance the story.
  Burton’s later years are chronicled in Jamie’s journal, found in Box 4, Folder 56. The four folders of condolences and the programs and readings from the memorial services (Box 3, Folders 35-40) offer a perspective on Burton’s interactions and relationships with many colleagues and friends, as well as his impact on Japanese studies, American-Japanese cultural relationships, and international relations.
  A scrapbook (Box 5, Folder 63) about Burton’s childhood, created by his mother Sophie, contains his parents’ letters and notes about Burton’s infancy and childhood, letters from Harvey to his children during his travels, and childhood and teenage letters to Harvey from Burton.
  Arrangement
  Files are arranged alphabetically by title, and thereunder chronologically.
  - Biography - "A Conversation with Charles Burton Fahs" and Chronology, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biography - "Charles Burton Fahs: Some Notes on the Life of an Uncommon Man", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biography - "Charles Burton Fahs: Scholar, Diplomat, Humanist: Notes on the Life of an International Man" (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biography -Draft by Jamie Ross Fahs and Barbara Fahs Charles -Foreword and Chapters 1-8, c. 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Biography - Draft of Chapter 9 "The Rockefeller Foundation Years", c. 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Biography - Draft of Chapter or Appendix "The Written and Spoken Word of Charles Burton Fahs" (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Biography - Correspondence Regarding Manuscript, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Biography - Research Materials on the Institute of Pacific Relations (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Biography - Research Materials for "The War Years" Chapter (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Childhood, 1908-1922, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Family Correspondence, 1908-1919, 1932, 1940, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence with Family, 1926 May-1928 June (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence with Family, 1928 July-August (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence with Family, 1928 September-1929 June (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence with Family, 1929 July-1930 August (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence with Family, 1930 September-1932 June (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence with Family, 1932 July, 1933 May and August (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Charles Burton Fahs and Jamie Ross Fahs Correspondence with Family, 1933 September-1934 May (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Charles Burton Fahs and Jamie Ross Fahs Correspondence with Family, 1934 June-1936 August (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence Regarding Study and Career Opportunities, 1929-1936 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence with Family, 1937 March-1940 March (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Jamie Ross Fahs Correspondence with Family and Travel Diary, 1940 September-December (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence with Family and Friends, 1940 October-November (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Jamie Ross Fahs Correspondence with Family, 1941 March-April (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence with Family, 1941 May-July (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Charles Burton Fahs and Jamie Ross Fahs Correspondence with Family, 1941 September-1945 November, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence - Annual Christmas Letter, 1951-1962 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Charles Burton Fahs and Jamie Ross Fahs Correspondence, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Charles Burton Fahs and Jamie Ross Fahs Correspondence, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Charles Burton Fahs and Jamie Ross Fahs Correspondence, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Charles Burton Fahs and Jamie Ross Fahs Correspondence, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Charles Burton Fahs and Jamie Ross Fahs Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence - Annual Christmas Letter, 1963-1980 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Charles Burton Fahs and Jamie Ross Fahs Correspondence with Family, 1970-1980 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Death - A Celebration of the Life of Charles Burton Fahs, 1980 March 1 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Death - A Service of Committal and Dedication in Honor of Charles Burton Fahs, 1980 August 22 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Death - Condolences from Family Members, 1980 February-March (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Death - Condolences Read at A Celebration of the Life of Charles Burton Fahs, 1980 March 1, 1980 February-March (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Death - Condolences, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Death - Condolences, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Death - Memorial Contributions, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Death - Memorial Guest Book from A Celebration of the Life of Charles Burton Fahs, 1980 March 1 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Death - Miami University Senate - A Memorial to Charles Burton Fahs, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Death - Obituaries and Press Notices, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Education - Northwestern University - Commencement Program, 1929 June 17 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Education - Northwestern University - Correspondence with Professor Ellingwood, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Education - Northwestern University - Correspondence Regarding Financial Aid, 1927, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Education - Northwestern University - Degrees, 1929, 1931, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Education - Northwestern University - Grade Report and Transcript, 1926, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Education - Northwestern University - Paper - "Karl Marx", 1929 May (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Education - Northwestern University - Papers for Graduate Classes, 1930-1933 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Education - University of Berlin - German Language Certification, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Identification Cards, 1933-1945 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Clippings Compiled by Jamie Ross Fahs, 1987-1992 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Correspondence Received by Jamie Ross Fahs, 1983-1993 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Jamie Ross Fahs Journal, 1977-1980, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Living Will, 1979 June 13 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Medical Records, 1940-1976 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Restricted from scholarly access.
  - Newspaper Article - "The Twain Does Meet - On Howard Avenue", 1962 January 17 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Passports, 1929-1978 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Passports - Correspondence, 1941, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Political Diary, 1931 December-1933 January (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Scrapbook - "Original Sources Relating to the Early Life of Charles Burton Fahs", 1838, 1908-1923 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Education - Northwestern University - Degrees, 1929, 1931, 1933 (Box 13, Folder 218)
- Professional papers, 1933-1973, 1980-1988; 2
  Folders in Series 2 document Burton’s varied career as an academic, a diplomat, and a foundation officer. There is minimal documentation for his tenure at Pomona College, the Office of Strategic Services and later Department of State, Muhlenberg College, and Grolier, Inc. More detailed information exists for his five years at Miami University, and extensive documentation is included for his career at the Rockefeller Foundation and the Embassy of the United States in Tokyo, Japan.
  The Rockefeller Foundation diaries are an incomplete set and are draft versions of the final diaries filed with the Rockefeller Foundation and found in their archives. The drafts do not appear to differ significantly from the final versions.
  Of interest in this series is Fahs’s report to John Marshall chronicling his train trip from Paris to Kyoto in 1934 (Box 6, Folder 85). The many reports and memoranda written by Fahs while at the Rockefeller Foundation and at Miami University offer his opinions on education, international study, and cultural exchange and evaluations of proposed changes to study abroad programs and support of universities in developing nations. The invitations and related materials from his time at the Embassy in Japan are also important items from his diplomatic career.
  Researchers interested in the early career of Charles Burton Fahs should also explore the correspondence files in Series 1 dated from this period; during his early career, there was an overlap between Fahs’s personal and professional life. Series 4, Manuscripts, Publications, and Speeches contains the many articles and book reviews written by Fahs during his time at Pomona College, as well as other articles and speeches made throughout his career.
  Files in this series are arranged chronologically, and thereunder alphabetically.
  - Curriculum Vitae and General Career Information, 1935-1972, 1980, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Pomona College, 1936-1946 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Pomona College, 1936-1939 (Box 5, Folder 65A)
  - Library of Congress/Coordinator of Information/Office of Strategic Services, 1941-1946 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Library of Congress/Coordinator of Information/Office of Strategic Services, 1941-1946 (Box 5, Folder 66A)
  - Department of State, 1946-1951 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Department of State, 1946-1951 (Box 5, Folder 67A)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Appointment and Promotions, 1945-1961 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Appointment and Promotions, 1945-1961 (Box 5, Folder 68A)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Centro Mexicano de Escritores, 1952, 1967-1992 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Diary - Trip to the Far East, 1950 April 12-June 14 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Diary - Trip to Latin America, 1950 September 30-October 25 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Diary - Trip to India and the Far East, 1951 January 12-March 5 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Diary - Trip to Mexico and Central America, 1951 October 1-28 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Diary - Trip to the Far East, 1952 April 5-June 6 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Diary - Trip to the Pacific Coast, 1952 August 31-September 24 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Diary - Trip to the Far East, 1953 April 6-June 6 (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Diary - Trip to Europe, 1954 January 23-February 2 (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Diary - Trip to the Far East, 1954 April 26-May 12 (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Diary - Trip to the Far East, 1955 April 15-May 24 (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Diary - Trip to the Far East, 1958 April 4-May 3 (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Diary - Trip to Southeast Asia, 1958 August 24-September 29 (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Diary - Trip to the Far East, 1959 April 4-25 (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Diary - Trip to England, 1959 October 11-19 (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - General, 1944-1968, undated (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - General Education Board Fellowship, 1933-1936, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Japanese Literary Fellowship Program, 1959, undated (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Memoranda for Department of State, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Memoranda and Reports, 1946-1961, undated (Box 6, Folder 88)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Memoranda and Reports - University Development Program, 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 89)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - National Diet Library, Japan, 1947-1951, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Resignation, 1961-1962 (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - Embassy of the United States, Tokyo, Japan - Activities, 1963-1967 (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - Embassy of the United States, Tokyo, Japan - Clippings, 1962-1968, undated (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - Embassy of the United States, Tokyo, Japan - Clippings from Japanese Newspapers (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Embassy of the United States, Tokyo, Japan - Correspondence, 1962-1967 (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Embassy of the United States, Tokyo, Japan - Invitations, 1962-1966 (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Embassy of the United States, Tokyo, Japan - Printed Materials, 1962-1967 (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - Embassy of the United States, Tokyo, Japan - Publicity, 1962-1963, 1967, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - Embassy of the United States, Tokyo, Japan - U.S. Information Agency Appointment, 1961-1967 (Box 7, Folder 99)
  - Embassy of the United States, Tokyo, Japan - U. S. Information Agency Appointment, 1962-1967 (Box 7, Folder 99A)
  - Muhlenberg College, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 100)
  - Miami University - Employment and Retirement, 1967-1973 (Box 7, Folder 101)
  - Miami University - Employment, 1967-1972 (Box 7, Folder 101A)
  - Miami University - International Studies Students, 1972, undated (Box 7, Folder 102)